<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A full and true account of the two great victories lately obtained before Lymerick, by K. William's forces over the French and Irish rebels, which were commanded by D. Tryconnel, and General Lauson with a particular relation of the killing seven hundred of the enemy, and the number of the prisoners taken, the flight of the rebels into the county of Clare, their horrid burnings, and other cruelties, and the number of the rebels hang'd for the same, by the command of Lieutenant General Douglas : in a letter from a gentleman, who was particularly concerned in the aforesaid action.</title>
            <author>P. W., Gentleman who was particularly concerned in the aforesaid action.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W88</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3367</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12630848</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12630848</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64758</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67625)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64758)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 678:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A full and true account of the two great victories lately obtained before Lymerick, by K. William's forces over the French and Irish rebels, which were commanded by D. Tryconnel, and General Lauson with a particular relation of the killing seven hundred of the enemy, and the number of the prisoners taken, the flight of the rebels into the county of Clare, their horrid burnings, and other cruelties, and the number of the rebels hang'd for the same, by the command of Lieutenant General Douglas : in a letter from a gentleman, who was particularly concerned in the aforesaid action.</title>
                  <author>P. W., Gentleman who was particularly concerned in the aforesaid action.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for G. Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Broadside.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>The letter is dated "Dvblin, August 4, 1690" and signed "P.W."</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
               <term>Tyrconnel, Richard Talbot, --  Earl of, 1630-1691.</term>
               <term>Lauzun, Antonin Nompar de Caumont, --  duc de, 1632 or 3-1723.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  War of 1689-1691.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  London --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:64758:1"/>
            <head>A Full and True ACCOUNT OF THE Two great Victories, Lately Obtained before <hi>Lymerick,</hi> BY K. William's Forces, Over the <hi>French and Iriſh Rebels.</hi> Which were commanded by D. Tyrconnel, and General Lauſon. WITH A Particular Relation of the Killing Seven Hundred of the Enemy, and the Number of the Priſoners taken: The Flight of the Rebels into the County of <hi>Clare.</hi> Their Horrid Burnings, and other Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties. And the Number of the Rebels Hang'd for the ſame, by the command of Lieutenant General <hi>Douglas.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">In a Letter from a Gentleman, who was particularly concerned in the aforeſaid Action.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</dateline>
               <lb/>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Fatigue of my Voyage, and the great hurry occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned hereby; the daily returns of our Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, in theſe parts, might very well Apologize for any neglect of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, at this preſent Juncture; but that your many Obligations to me, and my Family, and the Perſonal Knowledge I have of the longing Deſires of every one in <hi>England,</hi> to hear an Account of the Daily Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of our Heroical Prince's Arms here, makes me with Willingneſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get my own Troubles, to give you what Joy I can; and our Affairs here do adminiſter for the daily Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in his Glorious Undertakings: You have at leaſt two Poſts agone the certain News of thoſe places that
<pb facs="tcp:64758:2"/>have Surrendered, and are actually in our Poſſeſſion; the King having now little more than the Reduction of <hi>Lymerick;</hi> the Conſequence of which, is the entire Conqueſt of the Countrey; I ſhall conſine my ſelf to a true Relation of what has happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (near that place) ſince the join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Douglas</hi> to the <hi>Royal Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Iriſh</hi> that lay encamped about that place, and as it were under the Walls, were for Number between Twenty and Thirty Thouſand, and by their many Barbarous Cruelties to all the Proteſtants they could lay hands on, ſeem'd to defie the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and power of ſo formidable, and wear approaching Army, as our's are, but like true Cowards, when they were throughly convinc'd of our Strength, by the Courage of a detach'd party of five Hundred of our Troops, who advanc'd ſo reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, as to attack their Van Guard, conſiſting of near Two Thouſand Five Hundred, and killed near Six Hundred of them upon the Spot, and taking near Two Hundred pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, by which we may give a ſhrewd Gueſs, that they are not in any Meaſure improv'd, except in the Art of Running, ſince their Signal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat at the <hi>Boyne,</hi> for upon the retiring of their broken Troops to their main Body, the whole Army was in ſuch Conſternation, that if our Army had been a little nearer Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, we had put them out of condition of ever appearing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again; 'twas a pleaſant Sight to ſee the way ſcattered with Cloaks, Piſtols, Swords, Bagonets and Skeens, for ſome of them have no other Arms; and their Tents, ſuch as they had, and Baggage left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, they getting into the County of <hi>Clare,</hi> on the other ſide of <hi>Limer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick;</hi> ſo that we have nothing more now to do, than to lay a cloſe Siege, or to Bomb and Storm that place; which tis reaſonably thought, will not hold out long; for the Lord <hi>Tyrcetinel</hi> they ſay here, has ſent Propoſals of Submiſſion, but being very high, the King ſent him Word plainly to deliver up the Place, tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him he would give him a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and uſe him like a Gentleman, which he is to conſider off: The Rebels that were upon their Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Lieut. General <hi>Douglaſs</hi> from <hi>Athrone,</hi> very Inſolent and Cruel to the Proteſtants of that Country are pretty well quaſhed by Collonel <hi>Woſely,</hi> and Lieut. Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Purefoy</hi> of the Kings Councils, Four of which were hang'd up without further Tryal, having late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received the Kings Protection: The Army in general, but ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality more particularly are deſperately engaged againſt the Iriſh for their inhumane and Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous French way of Burning, War<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, Pulling-down, and Deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeveral ſine Seats in the County of <hi>Limmerick, viz. Kilpecken, Bruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, Ballyvorneene,</hi> and the Caſtle of <hi>Cappyneene,</hi> in the County of <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> in which Place they Burnt all the Goods, not ſuffering the Lady of, the place, to ſave ſo much as her wearing Apparel; for which Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barities our Army threatens very ſevere puniſhments, and nothing but the exhauſtible M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rcy of the King will be able to protect them from their juſt Fury: I hope by the next to give you a comfortable Account of <hi>Limmerick;</hi> till then, I Subſcribe my Self.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to Command, P. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CAtaſtrophe Galliae, &amp; Hiber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae Reſtitutio.</hi> An Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Judgment, Denoting the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of <hi>Ireland</hi> this Revolution <hi>90.</hi> (end-ing <hi>March</hi> the <hi>10th. 1691.</hi>) Alſo, The Conquering of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>XIV.</hi> preſent King of <hi>France,</hi> by His Sacred Majeſty K. <hi>WILLIAM</hi> the <hi>III.</hi> in a few Years. Prophetically deduced from the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Heaven. Printed for <hi>Tho. Howkins</hi> in <hi>George-Yard</hi> in <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard-ſtreet,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>R. Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old-Bayly, 1690.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for <hi>G. Smith</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
